<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1605-2528</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Ecología en Bolivia]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Ecología en Bolivia]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1605-2528</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Plural Editores ]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1605-25282013000100006</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Two unrelated species of birds (Myiopsitta monachus; Psittacidae and Coryphistera alaudina; Furnariidae) simultaneously building the same nest in the Paraguayan Chaco]]></article-title>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Dos especies de aves no emparentadas (Myiopsitta monachus; Psittacidae y Coryphistera alaudina; Furnariidae) construyen simultáneamente el mismo nido en el Chaco paraguayo]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Smith]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Paul]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Fretes]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Aldo]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,FAUNA Paraguay  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>Paraguay</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>48</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<fpage>52</fpage>
<lpage>56</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.org.bo/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1605-25282013000100006&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.org.bo/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1605-25282013000100006&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.org.bo/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1605-25282013000100006&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri></article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>NOTA</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="4"><b>Two unrelated species of birds <i>(Myiopsitta monachus; </i>Psittacidae</b></font> <b><font face="Verdana" size="4">and <i>Coryphistera alaudina; </i>Furnariidae) simultaneously building</font> <font face="Verdana" size="4">the same nest in the Paraguayan Chaco</font></b></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Dos especies de aves no emparentadas (<i>Myiopsitta monachus; </i>Psittacidae y <i>Coryphistera alaudina; </i>Furnariidae) construyen simultáneamente el mismo</b></font> <b><font face="Verdana" size="3">nido en el Chaco paraguayo</font></b></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Paul Smith<sup>1,2</sup> &amp; Aldo Fretes<sup>1</sup></b></font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><sup>1</sup>FAUNA Paraguay, <a href="mailto:www.faunaparaguay.com">www.faunaparaguay.com</a>     <br> <sup>2</sup>Para La Tierra, Reserva Natural Laguna Blanca, Municipalidad de Santa Bárbara,</font> <font face="Verdana" size="2">Departamento San Pedro, Paraguay     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   Corresponding author: </font><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><a href="mailto:paraguaybirds@yahoo.com.ar">paraguaybirds@yahoo.com.ar</a></font></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p> <hr noshade>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Monk Parakeet <i>(Myiopsitta monachus, </i>Psittacidae) is a widespread, sociable, parakeet that constructs conspicuous, communal, stick nests (Short 1975). Nests may be several meters in diameter, containing various separate nest chambers with entrances from the side and below and may be utilized by several pairs of parakeets at any one time (Juniper &amp; Parr 1998). In the Paraguayan dry Chaco, where the species is abundant, nests are built of spiny twigs such as <i>Celtis </i>sp. (Ulmaceae). Forshaw (1989) notes that, in addition to providing a defense against predators, a preference for thorny sticks may help the components to bind together more solidly. Nests are a common sight on electricity posts and the few larger tree species that occur in the area e.g. <i>Aspidosperma quebracho-blanco </i>(Apocynaceae) and <i>Chorisia insignis </i>(Bombacaceae) (Ratzlaff 2004). Individual trees may contain various nests that are added to continuously (Burger &amp; Gochfeld 2005), and on occasion such nests may become so large that they break the branches of the trees that sustain them (de la Peña 2010).</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Lark-like Brushrunner <i>(Coryphistera alaudina, </i>Furnariidae) is a common and conspicuous, semi-terrestrial Chaco resident that lives in family groups in brushy woodlands (Short 1975, Areta &amp; Bodrati 2007). This species builds large, globular, stick nests (30-50 x 30-35 cm) exposed in high trees, with the entrance on the upper side (de la Peña 2010). The natural history of this species was described in detail by Areta &amp; Bodrati (2007).</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Thorny twigs are utilized by many species of Furnariidae in the Chaco (Vaurie 1980, Narosky <i>et al. </i>1983). The exposed locations selected by some of these birds seem to advertise the presence of the nests, but protection is enhanced by selecting locations in tall trees, thorny cacti or otherwise inaccessible places (Vaurie 1980). Additionally, such nests may hang or incorporate false or elongated entrance tunnels making access to the nest chambers more difficult for potential predators (Vaurie 1980, Zykowski &amp; Prum 1999).</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Nest sharing (two species simultaneously inhabiting the same active nest), nest association (the close proximity of nests of two species) and nest reuse (utilizing an abandoned or usurped nest of another species) have been widely documented in South American birds (Lindell 1996, Oniki &amp; Willis 2003, Burger &amp; Gochfeld 2005, Nores 2009). In this note we document what is, to our knowledge, the first observation of two unrelated bird species simultaneously adding material to the same nest platform at an early stage of construction.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Observations took place on 11th September 2012 at Parque Nacional Teniente Agripino Enciso (Boquerón department, northern Paraguay). The study area consists of a clearing surrounded by low, arid thorn forest typical of the dry Chaco (Short 1975). The birds were observed for four hours (11 am to 3 pm) with 10 x 40 Minox binoculars by the authors. Detailed notes and photographs of observed behaviors were taken.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">The beginnings of a bowl-shaped nest platform (approximately 40 x 30 cm) were located on an outer branch of a large <i>Chorisia insignis </i>tree, adjacent to the accommodation block at the park headquarters. The tree already contained two other medium-sized parakeet nests, and an adjacent tree contained a large </font><font face="Verdana" size="2">nest of Brown Cacholote <i>(Pseudoseisura lophotes), </i></font><font face="Verdana" size="2">all constructed from similar thorny twigs. The ground below and around these nests was littered with twigs that presumably had fallen</font> <font face="Verdana" size="2">from these constructions or were rejected by their occupants.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">An adult <i>Myiopsitta </i>was observed to repeatedly depart some distance from the platform and return with thorny twigs. These were incorporated into the lower part of the construction by the birds. At the same time, at least three individuals of <i>Coryphistera </i>were observed collecting sticks from the ground in the area around the nest tree and flying up to the same nest platform on the upper side carrying a stick. On most occasions, birds entered into the nest out of sight of the observer, departing shortly after incorporating the stick into the nest. On two occasions birds were observed incorporating sticks into the outer part of the structure, confirming that they were involved in nest-building. When not actively nest building, both species were observed loafing on or near the nest platform, without apparent antagonism (<a href="#f1">Fig 1</a>).</font></p>     <p align="justify"><a name="f1"></a></p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/reb/v48n1/a06_figura_01.jpg" width="600" height="448"></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Avian species documented as associated with <i>Myiopsitta </i>nests in their native range include representatives of diverse families e.g. Ciconiidae (Burger &amp; Gochf eld 2005), Anatidae (Dabbene 1918, Friedman 1927, Port &amp; Brewer 2004), Falconidae (De Lucca 1984, Martella &amp; Bucher 1984, Forshaw 1989), Columbidae (Nores 2009), Cuculidae (Martella <i>et al. </i>1985), Tyrannidae (Martella <i>et al. </i>1985), Passeridae (P. Smith 2012 pers.obs.) and Icteridae (Martella <i>et al. </i>1985).</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Though nest chambers of parakeets may be occupied (Port &amp; Brewer 2004) or even sequestered (Martella &amp; Bucher 1984) by associating species, in some cases of nest sharing with larger bird species, it is the parakeet that uses the existing platform and not vice versa. A strong link between parakeet nests and <i>Jabiru mycteria </i>was noted by Burger &amp; Gochf eld (2005), with the parakeets adding material to the base of the existing stork nests. Similar behavior was documented in a feral parakeet population in Florida (USA) where nesting material was added to an Osprey <i>(Pandion haliaetus) </i>platform (Pranty 2009). Such plasticity in nesting habits has been mooted as a potential factor in the success <i>of Myiopsitta </i>as a feral bird (Pranty 2009).</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Areta &amp; Bodrati (2007) noted that all material for construction of at least one of their <i>Coryphistera </i>study nests was collected within 25 m of the nest site. <i>Myiopsitta </i>continually adds material to enlarge nests that are maintained as roost sites throughout the year (Nores 2009) and as a result, a super-abundance of fallen twigs accumulates below. Because of the considerable amount of material required to construct their bulky nests, species such as <i>Coryphistera, </i>which are unable to break large twigs directly from trees, may arguably benefit from locating their nests close to those of <i>Myiopsitta.</i></font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">This is the first documented direct association between <i>Myiopsitta </i>and <i>Coryphistera. </i>How the collaboration may have been initiated however is a matter for speculation. Whilst <i>Myiopsitta </i>has been observed to vigorously defend its nest against intruders (Port &amp; Brewer 2004,</font> <font face="Verdana" size="2">Nores 2009), Areta &amp; Bodrati (2007) noted that <i>Coryphistera </i>is a non-aggressive species that tolerates the presence of diverse species in the area around their nests, including potential predators. It may thus be hypothesized that the parakeets have utilized a platform established by <i>Coryphistera </i>in a desirable location of a tree already occupied by <i>Myiopsitta </i>nests as a base for the construction of a new nest.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">When nesting in trees, <i>Myiopsitta </i>shows a preference for taller trees with wider trunk diameters. Nest site selection characteristics that can be attributed to an improved structural security (nests in wider trees tend to fall down less often), weather constraints (avoidance of strong winds) and predator avoidance (Burger &amp; Gochfeld 2005). Whilst high winds are a common occurrence in the study area, the habitat characteristics of the dry Chaco means that the number of tall trees with wide trunks is limited, and hence suitable nest sites in trees may be in short supply. Bearing in mind the bulky nests that are built by the species, it may be hypothesized that <i>Coryphistera </i>shares these site selection criteria, thereby augmenting the probability of suitable sites for each species being in close proximity to each other.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Apart from the preference for similar building materials, certain aspects of the nest architecture make these two species potentially compatible in a nest-sharing scenario. The entrances to <i>Myiopsitta </i>nests are located in the lower part of the nest (Juniper &amp; Parr 1998), and their nests are constructed first by establishing a roof and then adding material to the underside of the structure (Burger &amp; Gochfeld 2005). In <i>Coryphistera </i>the entrance to the nest is on the upperside (de la Peña 2010), hence the nest is constructed first by establishing a base and then adding material to the sides to build the walls upwards, passing through a stage in which it resembles a large bowl (Areta &amp; Bodrati 2007). During our observations, both species were working in opposite directions without coming into direct contact with each other and hence avoiding disputes.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the Brazilian Pantanal, Burger &amp; Gochfeld (2005) noted nests of <i>Myiopsitta </i>as sometimes forming part of the nest of the Grey-crested Cacholote <i>(Pseudoseisura unirufa), </i>another Furnariid that builds a large stick nest (Zykowski &amp; Prum 1999). However, the authors did not detail the building process of those nests. There are no previous reports of <i>Coryphistera </i>nest sharing with any other species, and though the observation of nests incorporating those of <i>Pseudoseisura unirufa </i>may be considered an analogous situation in a related species, this is apparently the first reported observation of two species of birds simultaneously adding material to the same nest platform.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Acknowledgements</b></font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">We thank Mario Torales and the other park guards at Enciso National Park for their hospitality and assistance during our frequent visits.</font></p>     <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>References</b></font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Areta, J. I. &amp; A. Bodrati. 2007. Historia natural y comportamiento social del crestudo <i>(Coryphistera alaudina). </i>Ornitología Neotropical 18: 209-222.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Burger, J. &amp; M. Gochfeld. 2005. Nesting behaviour and nest site selection in monk parakeets <i>(Myiopsitta monachus) </i>in the Pantanal of Brazil. Acta Ethologica 8: 23-34.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Dabbene, R. 1918. Sobre una curiosa costumbre de nidificación del ‘<sup>‘</sup>pato barcino chico<sup>’</sup>’ <i>Nettium flavirostre </i>(Vieillot). Hornero 1: 111-114.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">De Lucca, E. R. 1984. Nidificación del halconcito colorado <i>(Falco sparverius) </i>en nidos de cotorra <i>(Myiopsitta monachus). </i>Hornero 13:238-240.</font></p>     <!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Forshaw, J.M. 1989. Parrots of the world . 3rd edit. Landsdowne Editions, Willoughby. 672 p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079245&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Friedman, H. 1927. Notes on some Argentine birds. Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology 68:139-236.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079246&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Juniper, T. &amp; M. Parr. 1998. Parrots: a guide to the parrots of the world. Pica Press, Sussex. 584 p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079247&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Lindell, C. 1996. Patterns of nest usurpation: When should species converge on nest niches? Condor 98: 464-473.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079248&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Martella, M. B. &amp; E. H. Bucher. 1984. Nesting of the spot-winged falconet in monk parakeet nests. The Auk 101: 614-615.</font></p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Martella, M. B., J. L. Navarro &amp; E. H. Bucher. 1985. Vertebrados asociados a los nidos de la cotorra <i>(Myiopsitta monachus) </i>en Córdoba y La Rioja. Physis, Sección C 43: 49-51.</font></p>     <!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Narosky, S., R. Fraga. &amp; M. de la Peña. 1983. Nidificación de las aves argentinas (Dendrocolaptidae y Furnariidae). Asociación Ornitológica del Plata, Buenos Aires. 98 p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079251&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Nores, M. 2009. Use of monk parakeet nests by common pigeons and response by the hosts. Wilson Journal of Ornithology 121: 812-815.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079252&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Oniki, Y. &amp; E.O. Willis. 2003. Re-uso de ninhos por aves neotropicais. Atualidades Ornitológicas 116: 4-7.</font></p>     <!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">de la Peña, M. R. 2010. Guía de nidos de aves del Paraguay. Guyra Paraguay, Asunción. 696 p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079254&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Port, J. L. &amp; G. L. Brewer. 2004. Use of monk parakeet <i>(Myiopsitta monachus) </i>nests by speckled teal <i>(Anas flavirostris) </i>in eastern Argentina. Ornitología Neotropical 15: 209-218.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Pranty, B. 2009. Nesting substrates of monk parakeets <i>(Myiopsitta monachus) </i>in Florida. Florida Field Naturalist 37: 51-57.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079256&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Ratzlaff, V. F. 2004. Una guía para plantas leñosas del Chaco. Iniciativa para la Investigación y Transferencia de Tecnologia Agraria Sostenible, Loma Plata. 136 p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079257&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Short, L. 1975. A zoogeographic analysis of the South American Chaco avifauna. Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 153:163-352.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079258&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Vaurie, C. 1980. Taxonomy and geographical distribution of the Furnariidae (Aves, Passeriformes).Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 166:1-357.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=079259&pid=S1605-2528201300010000600019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2">Zykowski, K. &amp;R. O. Prum. 1999. Phylogenetic analysis of the nest architecture of Neotropical ovenbirds (Furnariidae). Auk 116: 891-911.</font></p>     <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="justify"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Nota recibida en:</b> Octubre de 2012.     <br>   <b> Manejada por:</b> Lilian Painter.     <br>   <b>Aceptada en:</b> Enero de 2013.</font></p>     <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[ ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Areta]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.I.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Bodrati]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Historia natural y comportamiento social del crestudo (Coryphistera alaudina)]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Ornitología Neotropical]]></source>
<year>2007</year>
<numero>18</numero>
<issue>18</issue>
<page-range>209-222</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Burger]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Gochfeld]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Nesting behaviour and nest site selection in monk parakeets (Myiopsitta monachus) in the Pantanal of Brazil]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Acta Ethologica]]></source>
<year>2005</year>
<numero>8</numero>
<issue>8</issue>
<page-range>23-34</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Dabbene]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Sobre una curiosa costumbre de nidificación del ‘‘pato barcino chico’’ Nettium flavirostre (Vieillot)]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Hornero]]></source>
<year>1918</year>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>111-114</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[De Lucca]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Nidificación del halconcito colorado (Falco sparverius) en nidos de cotorra (Myiopsitta monachus)]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Hornero]]></source>
<year>1984</year>
<numero>13</numero>
<issue>13</issue>
<page-range>238-240</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Forshaw]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Parrots of the world]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<edition>3</edition>
<page-range>672</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Willoughby ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Landsdowne Editions]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Friedman]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Notes on some Argentine birds]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology]]></source>
<year>1927</year>
<numero>68</numero>
<issue>68</issue>
<page-range>139-236</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Juniper]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Parr]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Parrots: a guide to the parrots of the world]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<page-range>584</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Sussex ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Pica Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Lindell]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Patterns of nest usurpation: When should species converge on nest niches?]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Condor]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<numero>98</numero>
<issue>98</issue>
<page-range>464-473</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Martella]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.B.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Bucher]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Nesting of the spot-winged falconet in monk parakeet nests]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Auk]]></source>
<year>1984</year>
<numero>101</numero>
<issue>101</issue>
<page-range>614-615</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Martella]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.B.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Navarro]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.L.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Bucher]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Vertebrados asociados a los nidos de la cotorra (Myiopsitta monachus) en Córdoba y La Rioja]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Physis]]></source>
<year>1985</year>
<numero>43</numero>
<issue>43</issue>
<page-range>49-51</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Narosky]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Fraga]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[de la Peña]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Nidificación de las aves argentinas (Dendrocolaptidae y Furnariidae)]]></source>
<year>1983</year>
<page-range>98</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Buenos Aires ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Asociación Ornitológica del Plata]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Nores]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Use of monk parakeet nests by common pigeons and response by the hosts]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Wilson Journal of Ornithology]]></source>
<year>2009</year>
<numero>121</numero>
<issue>121</issue>
<page-range>812-815</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Oniki]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Y.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Willis]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.O.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Re-uso de ninhos por aves neotropicais]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Atualidades Ornitológicas]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<numero>116</numero>
<issue>116</issue>
<page-range>4-7</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[de la Peña]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Guía de nidos de aves del Paraguay]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<page-range>696</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Asunción ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Guyra Paraguay]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Port]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.L.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Brewer]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.L.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Use of monk parakeet (Myiopsitta monachus) nests by speckled teal (Anas flavirostris) in eastern Argentina]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Ornitología Neotropical]]></source>
<year>2004</year>
<numero>15</numero>
<issue>15</issue>
<page-range>209-218</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Pranty]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Nesting substrates of monk parakeets (Myiopsitta monachus) in Florida]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Florida Field Naturalist]]></source>
<year>2009</year>
<numero>37</numero>
<issue>37</issue>
<page-range>51-57</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ratzlaff]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Una guía para plantas leñosas del Chaco. Iniciativa para la Investigación y Transferencia de Tecnologia Agraria Sostenible]]></source>
<year>2004</year>
<page-range>136</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Loma Plata ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Short]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[L.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[A zoogeographic analysis of the South American Chaco avifauna]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History]]></source>
<year>1975</year>
<numero>153</numero>
<issue>153</issue>
<page-range>163-352</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Vaurie]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Taxonomy and geographical distribution of the Furnariidae (Aves, Passeriformes)]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History]]></source>
<year>1980</year>
<numero>166</numero>
<issue>166</issue>
<page-range>1-357</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Zykowski]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[K.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Prum]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.O.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Phylogenetic analysis of the nest architecture of Neotropical ovenbirds (Furnariidae)]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Auk]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<numero>116</numero>
<issue>116</issue>
<page-range>891-911</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
